Guide to the Eugene Parker Papers 1948-2018
University of Chicago Library
Parker, Eugene. Papers
1948-2018
12.5 linear feet (18 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
Eugene Parker was an astrophysicist and University of Chicago professor best known for predicting the existence of solar wind. In addition to heliophysics, Parker also studied cosmic rays and magnetic fields. The collection includes Parker’s email correspondence; scientific and personal photographs; reprints of Parker’s scientific publications from 1952 to 2016; lecture notes and overhead projector slides from Parker’s courses; materials related to astrophysicist Subrahmanyan Chandrasekhar; scientific publications written by others; and Parker’s awards and diplomas. Materials date between 1948 and 2018, with the bulk of material dating between 1952 and 2011.
Information on Use
Access
This collection is open for research with the exception of material in Series X. This series contains Parker’s letters of recommendation, which are restricted for 80 years from the date of record creation.
Biographical Note
Eugene Newman Parker was born on June 10, 1927 in Houghton, Michigan. His father, Glenn Parker, worked as an engineer at Chrysler and his mother, Helen Parker (MacNair) worked as a homemaker. Parker earned a B.S. in Physics from Michigan State University in 1948 and a PhD from the California Institute of Technology in 1951.
In 1954, Eugene married Niesje Parker. The couple had one son, Eric Parker, and one daughter, Joyce Marie Parker.
After finishing his PhD, Parker worked at the University of Utah as an instructor and assistant professor. He was hired by the University of Chicago in 1955, where he worked for the rest of his career. In 1958, Parker published his prediction of the existence of solar wind, a continuous outpouring of charged particles flowing from the sun at a million miles per hour. His idea was met with widespread skepticism from fellow physicists, including the reviewers of the paper and the editor of the publication. Parker’s prediction was verified, however, when NASA’s Mariner II spacecraft encountered a flow of solar particles during its flight to Venus in 1962.
In addition to heliophysics, Parker also studied cosmic rays and magnetic fields. His four books include Interplanetary Dynamical Processes (1963), Cosmical Magnetic Fields: Their Origin and Their Activity (1979), Spontaneous Current Sheets in Magnetic Fields, with Applications to Stellar X-rays (1994), and Conversations on Electric and Magnetic Fields in the Cosmos (2007). He retired in 1995 but continued to teach and publish work in the following decades.
Parker won numerous awards throughout his career, including the National Medal of Science, the Kyoto Prize, and the American Physical Society Medal for Exceptional Achievement in Research. He was member of the National Academy of Sciences and served as chair for the Academy’s astronomy section. In 2017, NASA named its solar probe the Parker Solar Probe in his honor, marking the first time NASA named a spacecraft after a living person.
Eugene Parker died in Chicago on March 15, 2022 at the age of 94.
Scope Note
The Eugene Parker Papers are organized into ten series: Series I: Personal; Series II: Correspondence; Series III: Writing; Series IV: Teaching; Series V: Professional Associations and Events; Series VI: Writing by Others; Series VII: Awards, Honors, and Degrees; Series VIII: Audiovisual; Series IX: Oversize; and Series X: Restricted. The collection includes Parker’s email correspondence; reprints of Parker’s scientific publications from 1952 to 2016; lecture notes and overhead projector slides from Parker’s courses; materials related to astrophysicist Subrahmanyan Chandrasekhar; scientific publications written by others; scientific and personal photographs; and Parker’s awards and diplomas. Materials date between 1948 and 2018, with the bulk of material dating between 1952 and 2011.
Series I, Personal, contains biographical and autobiographical information on Parker and ephemera.
Series II, Correspondence, contains Parker’s letters, handwritten notes, and printed emails, including correspondence related to the Parker Solar Probe.
Series III, Writing, contains Parker’s thesis manuscript, reprinted papers, reports, articles, publications, and pamphlets. Reprinted papers are ordered roughly chronologically. All other writing is organized chronologically following the reprinted papers.
Series IV, Teaching, contains Parker’s lecture notes and overhead projector slides from the 2000s and 2010s. Materials are organized alphabetically according to the lecture title.
Series V, Professional Associations and Events, contains materials related to Parker’s professional life, such as newsletters, bulletins, dinner lists and menus, and symposium programs. Organizations include but are not limited to the Instrument Society of America, the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, and the NATO Advanced Study Institute on Solar and Astrophysical Magnetohydrodynamic Flows. Materials are arranged chronologically.
Series VI, Writing by Others, contains materials concerning other astrophysicists and scientific publications not written by Eugene Parker. Materials are divided into two subseries:
Subseries 1, Materials Related to Other Astrophysicists, contains reprints by and memorials to Subrahmanyan Chandrasekhar, reprints and correspondence with Joseph Lemaire, and reprints by Sydney Chapman. Materials are arranged alphabetically according to the last name of the astrophysicist.
Subseries 2, Scientific Publications, contains copies of the publication The Planetary Report (1983-1985) and other scientific articles and pamphlets, including materials published by NASA. Materials are arranged roughly chronologically.
Series VII, Awards, Honors, and Degrees, contains awards, medals, and degrees granted to Parker, as well as his university degrees, diplomas, certificates, and acceptance speeches. Material are arranged chronologically according to the award date.
Series VIII, Audiovisual, contains Parker’s scientific and personal photographs from 1965 to 2000 and a DVD recording of a workshop.
Series IX, Oversize, contains oversized materials such as framed awards, diplomas, and honorary degrees. Materials are organized according to size.
Series X, Restricted, contains Parker’s letters of recommendation, which are restricted for 80 years from the date of record creation. Materials are organized chronologically.
Related Resources
Browse finding aids by topic.
Subrahmanyan Chandrasekhar Papers
Peter Meyer Papers
David N. Schramm Papers
Lalitha Chandrasekhar Papers
Edwin B. Frost Papers
George Ellery Hale Papers
George van Biesbroeck Papers
Henry Gordon Gale Papers
University of Chicago Division of the Physical Sciences Records
University of Chicago Yerkes Observatory Logbooks and Notebooks
Subject Headings
Parker, E.N. (Eugene Newman), 1927-2022; Chandrasekhar, S. (Subrahmanyan), 1910-1995; National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA); University of Chicago. Department of Astronomy and Astrophysics; American Physical Society; National Academy of Sciences (U.S.); Astrophysics; Astrophysicists; Solar wind
INVENTORY
- Series I: Personal
  This series contains biographical and autobiographical information on Parker and ephemera.
  - Biographical Information, CV, and Correspondence, 1997-2013 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Solar Eclipse Viewers, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Images from the Chandra X-Ray Observatory Calendar, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series II: Correspondence
  This series contains Parker’s letters, handwritten notes, and printed emails, including correspondence related to the Parker Solar Probe.
  - Correspondence, 1990-2016 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence Related to Parker Solar Probe, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series III: Writing
  This series contains Parker’s thesis manuscript, reprinted papers, reports, articles, publications, and pamphlets. Reprinted papers are ordered roughly chronologically. All other writing is organized chronologically following the reprinted papers.
  - Reprinted Papers 1-44, 1952-1961 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Reprinted Papers 45-75, 1960-1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Reprinted Papers 76-97, 1963-1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Reprinted Papers 98-124, 1965-1968 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Reprinted Papers 125-142, 1968-1970 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Reprinted Papers 143-184, 1969-1975 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Reprinted Papers 185-201, 1974-1977 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Reprinted Papers 202-228, 1978-1982 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Reprinted Papers 229-259, 1981-1985 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Reprinted Papers 260-276, 1985-1987 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Reprinted Papers 277-291, 1987-1989 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Reprinted Papers 292-301, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Reprinted Papers 302-319, 1990-1993 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Reprinted Papers 320-336, 1992-1996 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Reprinted Papers 337-340, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Reprinted Papers 341-349, 1994-1996 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Reprinted Papers 350-354, 1995-1997 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Reprinted Papers 355-361, 1996-1997 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Reprinted Papers 361-376, 1997-2000 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Reprinted Papers 377-389, 1999-2002 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Reprinted Papers 390-392, 2001-2004 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Reprinted Papers 391-396, 2002-2006 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Reprinted Papers 394-408, 2006-2012 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Reprinted Papers 410, 2013 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Reprinted Papers 411-412, 2016 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Thesis Manuscript — Interstellar Dust and Gas Clouds, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Research on Global Warming, circa 1990s [1/2] (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Research on Global Warming, circa 1990s [2/2] (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Assessing the Changing Moods of the Sun and the Climate of Earth, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - A History of the Solar Wind Concept, 2001 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Parker Wind, 2008 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Hydrodynamics and the Kinetic Treatment of a Collisionless Atmosphere, 2008 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Solar Activity: From Galileo’s Sunspots to the Heliosphere, 2009 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - The Legacy of Jack Eddy, 2010 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Wherefore Physics? 2011 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Physics and the World, circa 2011 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Diverse Scientific Contributions, undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Citations and Notes, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Series IV: Teaching
  This series contains Parker’s lecture notes and overhead projector slides from the 2000s and 2010s. Materials are organized alphabetically according to the lecture title.
  - The Applicability of Hydrodynamics — Lecture Notes and Overhead Projector Slides, circa 2000s (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - A Brief History of the Dynamo Concept — Lecture Notes and Overhead Projector Slides, circa 2000s (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Cosmic Rays and Space Travelers — Lecture Notes and Overhead Projector, circa 2006 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Discovery and Investigation of Solar Magnetism — Lecture Notes and Overhead Projector Slides, circa 2000s (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Electromagnetic Preliminaries and Ongoing Developments in Plasma Physics — Lecture Notes and Overhead Projector Slides, circa 2010s (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Fifty Years of Galactic Magnetic Field — Lecture Notes and Overhead Projector Slides, circa 2000s (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Galileo and the Physics of the Heliosphere — Lecture Notes and Overhead Projector Slides, circa 2000s (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - History of the Solar Wind — Lecture Notes and Overhead Projector Slides, circa 2000s (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - The Legacy of Jack Eddy — Lecture Notes and Overhead Projector Slides, circa 2000s (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - The Microworld of the Solar Corona — Lecture Notes and Overhead Projector Slides, circa 2000s (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Pathological Science in Physics Today — Article and Lecture Notes, circa 2000s (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Poynting Theorem and Introduction to Plasma Physics and Sociology — Lecture Notes and Overhead Projector Slides, circa 2000s (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - The Secret Life of Magnetic Fields — Lecture Notes and Overhead Projector Slides, circa 2000s (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Solar Magnetism — Book Outline, Lecture Notes, and Overhead Projector Slides, 2008 [1/2] (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Solar Magnetism — Book Outline, Lecture Notes, and Overhead Projector Slides, 2008 [2/2] (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Solar Wind — Lecture Notes and Overhead Projector Slides, circa 2008 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Space Exploration and Cosmic Rays — Lecture Notes and Overhead Projector Slides, circa 2000s (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Sun, Earth, and Magnetic Fields — Lecture Notes and Overhead Projector Slides, circa 2000s (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Untitled — Lecture Notes and Overhead Projector Slides on Solar Wind, circa 2000s (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - What are Stellar and Galactic Dynamos to do Without Turbulent Diffusion of Magnetic Fields? — Lecture Notes and Overhead Projector Slides, circa 2005 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Series V: Professional Associations and Events
  This series contains materials related to professional association and events, such as newsletters, bulletins, dinner lists and menus, and symposium programs. Organizations include but are not limited to the Instrument Society of America, the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, and the NATO Advanced Study Institute on Solar and Astrophysical Magnetohydrodynamic Flows. Materials are arranged chronologically.
  - The Instrument Society of America Events Newsletter, 1963 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Ryerson Astronomical Society Club Dinner Lists, 1979 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - The American Academy of Arts and Sciences Bulletin, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - University of Oslo Annual Report and Annual Party Materials, 1990 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - NATO Advanced Study Institute on Solar and Astrophysical Magnetohydrodynamic Flows Dinner Menu, 1995 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Nobel Laureates from the Chicago Physics Department and the Research Institutes Booklet, 1995 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Challenging the Paradigm: The Legacy of Galileo Symposium Program, 2009 (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Series VI: Writing by Others
  This series contains materials concerning other astrophysicists and scientific publications not written by Eugene Parker. The first subseries contains reprints by and memorials to Subrahmanyan Chandrasekhar, reprints and correspondence with Joseph Lemaire, and reprints by Sydney Chapman. Materials are arranged alphabetically according to the last name of the astrophysicist. The second subseries contains copies of the publication The Planetary Report (1983-1985) and other scientific articles and pamphlets, including materials published by NASA. Materials are arranged roughly chronologically.
  - Subseries 1: Materials Related to Other Astrophysicists
    - Subrahmanyan Chandrasekhar Reprints and Memorials, 1975-2010 [1/6] (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Subrahmanyan Chandrasekhar Reprints and Memorials, 1975-2010 [2/6] (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Subrahmanyan Chandrasekhar Reprints and Memorials, 1975-2010 [3/6] (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Subrahmanyan Chandrasekhar Reprints and Memorials, 1975-2010 [4/6] (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Subrahmanyan Chandrasekhar Reprints and Memorials, 1975-2010 [5/6] (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Subrahmanyan Chandrasekhar Reprints and Memorials, 1975-2010 [6/6] (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Sydney Chapman Reprints, 1971 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Joseph Lemaire Reprints and Correspondence, 1973-2008 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Subseries 2: Scientific Publications
    - Scientific Reprints and Articles, 1952-2009 [1/2] (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Scientific Reprints and Articles, 1952-2009 [2/2] (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Advertising Pamphlet for Fourth Edition of Exploration of the Universe, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Science and Creationism: A View from the National Academy of Sciences, 1984 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - The Planetary Report Magazine, 1983-1984 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Physics World with Survey Thank You Note sent to Eugene Parker, 1999 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Ian Lerche — Cosmic Connections: A Scientific Autobiography, 2005 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - NASA Publications, 1979-2018 (Box 9, Folder 10)
- Series VII: Awards, Honors, and Degrees
  This series contains awards, medals, and degrees granted to Parker, as well as his university degrees, diplomas, certificates, and acceptance speeches. Material are arranged chronologically according to the award date.
  - B.S. — Michigan State University, 1948 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Election to National Academy of Sciences Documents, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - American Geophysical Union John Adam Fleming Award Programs, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - NASA Apollo Achievement Award, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Michigan State University Commencement Documents, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Chapman Medal Presidential Address Transcript, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - California Institute of Technology Alumni Award, 1980 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - National Medal of Science Election Documents, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Bowie Medal Photograph and Announcement, 1989-1990 [1/2] (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Bowie Medal Photograph and Announcement, 1989-1990 [2/2] (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - American Geographical Union Parker Lecture Certificate, 1991 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - MIT Hannes Alfvén Lecturer Award, 1992 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Kyoto Prize Materials, 2003 [1/3] (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Kyoto Prize Materials, 2003 [2/3] (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Kyoto Prize Materials, 2003 [3/3] (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - American Physical Society Exceptional Achievement Ceremony and Reception Program, 2018 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - National Research Council Space Studies Board Certificate of Appreciation, undated (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Michigan State University Jonathan L. Snyder Society Award, 2003 (Box 11)
- Series VIII: Audiovisual
  This series contains Parker’s scientific and personal photographs from 1965 to 2000 and a DVD recording of a workshop.
  - Personal and Scientific Photographs, 1965-2000 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - DVD — Parker Workshop on Magnetic Reconnection — São Paulo, Brazil, 2014 (Box 12, Folder 2)
- Series IX: Oversize
  This series contains oversized materials such as framed awards, diplomas, and honorary degrees. Materials are organized according to size.
  - American Geophysical Union Recognition of Eminence, 1962 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - American Institute of Aeronautics and Astronautics Space Science Award, 1964 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - National Academy of Sciences Diploma, 1967 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - American Geophysical Union John Adam Fleming Award, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Utrecht University Honorary Doctorate and Ceremony Photographs, 1986 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - National Medal of Science Diploma, 1989 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Oslo University Honorary Doctorate, 1991 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Framed NASA Public Service Award, 2017 (Box 13)
  - Det Norske Videnskaps-Akademi Member Diploma, 1988 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - American Physical Society Exceptional Achievement in Research Prize, 2018 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Framed Village of Flossmoor Commendation, 2017 (Box 14)
  - American Physical Society James Clerk Maxwell Award, 2003 (Box 15)
  - European Physical Society Hannes Alfvén Award, 2012 (Box 15)
  - National Observatory of Athens Moon Chart, 2013 (Box 15)
  - Kyoto Prize, 2003 (Box 16)
  - Kyoto Prize Album of Memories (Box 16)
  - Seven Wise Men of the World in Cosmology Greek Award, Case, and Medal 2008 (Box 17)
- Series X: Restricted
  This series contains Parker’s letters of recommendation which are restricted for 80 years from the date of record creation. Materials are organized chronologically.
  - Letters of Recommendation, 2002-2006 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Letters of Recommendation, 2007-2009 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Letters of Recommendation, 2010-2012 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Letters of Recommendation, 2013-2015 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Letters of Recommendation, 2016-2017 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Letters of Recommendation, circa 2010s (Box 18, Folder 6)